Guide to the Professor Bette Ann Stead Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Professor Bette Ann Stead Papers
1967-2007
2001-013
Stead, Bette Ann, 1935-
1.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection primarily contains announcements, scholarly journal articles, newsletters, and newspaper clippings, the majority pertaining to Dr. Stead's academic contributions as well as her efforts to establish FHPW and GHBER.
Biographical Information:
Dr. Bette Ann Stead, known as the Architect for C.T. Bauer's $40 million endowment, is professor emerita of the C. T. Bauer College of Business, University of Houston, where she taught for 34 years. Dr. Stead's numerous articles have been published in the Academy of Management Journal, Business Horizons, Group and Organization Management, IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, IEEE Transactions on Professional Communication, Journal of Business Ethics, Information and Optimization Sciences, Journal of Library Administration, Journal of Nonprofit and Public Sector Marketing, Library Quarterly, Vital Speeches of the Day, etc. In 1978, she co-authored Business English and Communication (McGraw-Hill). Also in 1978, Stead published the first edition of Women in Management (Prentice Hall), which she used in her "Women in Administration" course. In 1985, the second edition was published.
In 1975, when Dr. Stead began teaching her groundbreaking course, "Women in Administration," women were denied membership in business and service organizations. On March 31, 1981, Dr. Stead presented a suggested constitution and bylaws to representatives from 20 business and scientific women’s organizations, which was used to establish the Federation of Houston Professional Women (FHPW), in September of that year. FHPW now has some fifty member organizations. http://www.fhpw.org/our_history.html
In 1989, while serving as the Director of the Institute for Business, Ethics, and Public Issues, Dr. Stead presented a concept statement suggesting that the business school could bring together company representatives to discuss ethical concerns. There was very little interest in establishing such an organization. On October 26 1995, she again forwarded her concept statement regarding the establishment of the Greater Houston Business Ethics Roundtable (GHBER). This time, Dr. Stead did receive a positive response from local businesses. Shortly thereafter, GHBER was established to highlight the pivotal role of ethics in the workplace and to share "best practices." On November 16, 1999, GHBER presented Dr. Stead with the "1999 Dedicated Service Award," due to her efforts in creating this organization. In 2006 on GHBER's Tenth Anniversary, five $1000 scholarships were named in her honor. "The GHBER Bette Stead Scholarships" recognize her tireless dedication to education as well as the decisive role she played in establishing this organization. These 5 scholarships are awarded to Houston-area MBA students, and numerous major corporations belong to GHBER today. http://www.ghber.org.
In 1999, Dr. Stead became the architect of the capital campaign needs assessment that led to C.T. Bauer's $40 million endowment of the University of Houston's College of Business Administration. She has endowed three memorial scholarships in the C. T. Bauer College of Business honoring her aunt, paternal grandparents, and parents. These scholarships are managed by the Cougar Investment Fund, L.L.C., which allows graduate students to gain valuable experience in money-management.
Dr. Stead has received the Distinguished Faculty Member Award, C. T. Bauer College of Business Alumni Association; Melcher Faculty Service Fellow for outstanding service productivity and contributions to field, 1992-1993, 1993-1994, 1996-1997, 1997-1998, 1999-2000; Melcher Award for Excellence in Service for accomplishments and contributions in all dimensions of professional service, 1995; Senior Service Award for outstanding service as mentor, scholar, and role model, Women in Management Division, Academy of Management, 1992; and was named Distinguished Alumna, Lamar University, 2004. She has endowed three memorial scholarships in the Lamar University College of Business honoring her aunt, paternal grandparents, and parents. In 1970 she guided the work that won the MBA Magazine award, for best graduate research by a business student in the U. S. ($700 for student; $500 for UH Library). She also was invited to the White House July 1, 1976, to attend the International Women's Year report ceremony presentation to President Gerald R. Ford. In June 12-16, 1972, she was a participant in the "Global Strategy Discussions," Naval War College, Newport, Rhode Island.
She developed a course called "Marketing for Nonprofits." Her students completed over 150 projects for Houston-area nonprofits. Her community service also includes being president, River Oaks Business Women's Exchange Club, 1991; president, advisory board, The Women's Home (founded 1957), 501 (c)(3), only agency in Houston offering women long-term residential care, psychiatric and nurse practitioner services, psychotherapy, chemical dependency services and vocational and spiritual development programs, 2002-2004; president, board of directors, Houston Compass, Inc., (501 (c)(3) provides job leads, bus tokens, and legal aid for street people; president, board of directors, Christ Church Cathedral (Episcopal) Endowment, 2003. She chaired the $2M renovation of Christ Church Cathedral, 1994. She also chaired the $4M capital expansion (1999) as well as the $10M affordable housing project (2001-now) for The Women's Home.
She has also published, The Adventures of December, The Women's Home Cat, about a real cat that has lived at The Women’s Home for some 20 years; and C. C. Billy Goat and the First Christ Church, based on an 1852 painting by Thomas Flintoff of the first Christ Church, which stands where Christ Church Cathedral stands today. She has gifted the first printing and copyright for both stories to these organizations.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston -- Faculty; University of Houston. College of Business Administration
Genre/Form of Material:
Agendas (administrative records); Articles; Brochures; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Faculty papers; Fliers (printed matter); Lectures; Newspapers
Personal Name:
Stead, Bette Ann, 1935-
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Dr. Bette Ann Stead
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Federation of Houston Professional Women Records, 1998-006 http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcardandid=347
Written as Degree Requirements:
Although not part of this collection, the researcher may wish to examine two other scholarly works by Dr. Stead, which are housed in Special Collections. Both of these items are typescripts, which she submitted to fulfill degree requirements for the Doctor of Education degree.
"Galveston Bay: The Race to Save a Resource," TD224.T4S73 1966
A Computer Approach to University Curriculum Design for Administrative Management, Thesis 370 1967.S799
Arrangement of Materials:
There is some overlap between the information in several of the series, especially Honors and Awards, Accomplishments and Recognition, Organization Affiliations, and Community Activism, and so the researcher should cross-check and correlate the information from the various series.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily contains announcements, scholarly journal articles, newsletters, and newspaper clippings, the majority pertaining to Dr. Stead's academic contributions as well as her efforts to establish FHPW and GHBER. The material has been arranged into 9 series: Miscellaneous; Degree Requirements; Academic Projects; Training/Workshops; Scholarly Works; Honors and Awards; Accomplishments and Recognition; Organization Affiliations; Community Activism.
Detailed List of Contents
- Miscellaneous
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of two folders pertaining to matters not related to events covered in this finding aid. The correspondence folder contains the draft of a recommendation letter and a few article clippings. Of note is a copy of an early resume by Dr. Stead, which mentions her academic activities before joining the UH faculty.
  - Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resume (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Academic Projects
  This series consists of 5 folders pertaining to Dr. Stead's academic contributions, which include college- and graduate-level courses, seminar presentations, conference papers and panels on which she has served. Although the folders in this series contain mainly newspaper clippings and correspondence relating to her academic activities, there are syllabi and course descriptions for the course on "Women in Administration."
  - "SOM 436 and SOM 636/00354: Women in Administration," UH College of Business Administration, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "GENB 7336: Women in Administration," UH College of Business Administration, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "MARK 4377: Business and Public Issues," and "MARK 7397: Marketing for Non-Profits,", 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Seminars, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conference Papers and Panel Discussions, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Training/Workshops
  This series consists of 12 folders arranged chronologically from 1974 to 1979 and they pertain to training and workshops focusing on women's professional development. Although most of the folders in this series contain event programs, correspondence and newspaper clippings, one folder also holds evaluation forms, which may be of interest to the researcher.
  - "Administrative Internships for UH Women," Systems and Operations Management Department, 1974-1975, "UH Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration: Women in Management Day," UH College of Business Administration, June 16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Women's Problems in Gaining Management Positions," Rotary Club Meeting and Luncheon, June 16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drafts of Introductory Remarks by Dr. Stead (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press/Press Releases (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thank You Letters, "Management Development Center Program for UH Academic and Professional Women," UH College of Business Administration, April 7 and May 5, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Program of Events (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Thank You Letters, "A Case Approach to Managing the Qualified Career Woman," UH Administrative Development Program, April 11 and November 28, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Program Packet (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Evaluation Forms (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Scholarly Works
  This series consists of 5 folders pertaining to Stead's scholarly research, especially in the areas of grammar usage, business communication and women's professional advancement. This series is further subdivided into two sub-series, "Books" and "Articles," respectively. The books listed immediately below have been catalogued and placed in the stacks. As with "Academic Projects," this series also contains newsletters as well as copies or off-prints of journal articles.
  - Easy Grammar: A Programmed Review, PE1112.W64 1969, Business English and Communication, PE1115.B845 1978, Women in Management, HF5500.3.U54.W648, Women in Management, HD38.25.U6.W66 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Books
  - Easy Grammar: A Programmed Review, PE1112.W64 1969, Business English and Communication, PE1115.B845 1978,Women in Management, HF5500.3.U54.W648, Women in Management, HD38.25.U6.W66 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Articles
  - Delta Pi Epsilon Journal, Information and Records Management, Journal of Business Communication, Business Automation, ABCA Journal of Business Communication, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Supervisory Management, Journal of Business Education, Academy of Management Journal, Vital Speeches of the Day, Business Horizons, Academy of Management Proceedings, Journal of Business Communication, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Library Quarterly, Vital Speeches of the Day, Office Administration and Automation, Journal of Business Ethics, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    This folder also includes Dr. Stead's unpublished review of The Assertive Librarian, Z682.C26 1984.
  - Journal of Business Ethics, Business Horizons, Group and Organization Management, 1990-2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Honors and Awards
  This series consists of 7 folders pertaining to honors and awards Dr. Stead has received. With the exception of the FHPW folder, which also holds a banquet program, the others contain correspondence, newsletters or college magazine articles documenting her professional advancement.
  - Board of Directors, Southwest Federation of Administrative Disciplines, Acta Diurna, April 3, 1975, Faculty Promotion from Associate Professor to Professor, Systems and Operations Management Department, Acta Diurna, May 8, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “A Salute to Women and their Vision of International Houston,” FHPW, Seventh Annual Awards Banquet, October 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Senior Service Award, Women in Management Division of the Academy of Management, Melcher Monthly, Summer 1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Melcher Faculty Service Fellow, UH College of Business Administration, MelcherMonthly, May 1992 and 1993, Melcher Award for Faculty Excellence in Service, UH College of Business Administration, From the Dean, Summer 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Distinguished Faculty Member, College of Business Alumni Association, Houston Alumline, Winter 2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Distinguished Alumna," Lamar University, Cardinal Cadence, June-August 2004 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Accomplishments and Recognition
  This series consists of 7 folders acknowledging Dr. Stead's accomplishments and recognition. Although these folders largely contain college magazine articles, two also hold the text of Stead's speeches marking the establishment of scholarships in her honor.
  - Quoted in "Now, More than Ever, Partnership Must Remember its Mission," and "Unpaid Leave: A Family Values Dilemma," Houston Post, January 9, 1991 and September 27, 1992, Quoted in "Seminar Tips UH on Internet," The Daily Cougar, January 26, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Proclamation of Appreciation," The Women’s Home $4 Million Capital Expansion, The Quarterly Magazine of Alpha Chi Omega, Summer 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Architect of Capital Campaign Proposal," $40 Million Endowment of C.T. Bauer College of Business, Collegium Spring 2002 and Bauer College of Business 2003 Annual Report (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Lucy Ella Stead Memorial Scholarship," UH Scholarship Gala, Cougar Investment Fund, 2003 Annual Report and Bauer College of Business 2004 Annual Report (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "College of Business Foundation Scholarship," Cougar Investment Fund, 2005 Annual Report (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Cougar Fund Board of Managers Recognition," Bauer College of Business Leadership Program, April 20, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "GHBER Bette Stead Scholarship," GHBER 10th Anniversary Celebration, November 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Organization Affiliations
  This series consists of 7 folders pertaining to Dr. Stead's significant involvement in various women's organizations in the Houston area. In particular, because Stead played a vital role in FHPW and GHBER, the folders below also hold drafts of the bylaws she created to establish these organizations. Further, it is interesting to note that the ROBWEC folder contains a 1991 photograph of Stead and Geraldine Ferraro, a former Democratic Vice-Presidential candidate.
  - University of Houston Academic and Professional Women's Association (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - College of Business Administration Alumni: Women's Interest Network (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - River Oaks Business Women's Exchange Club (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Houston Association of Working Women's Associations (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Federation of Houston Professional Women (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - FHPW Awards Banquet Programs for 1991 and 2006 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Greater Houston Business Ethics Roundtable (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Community Activism
  This series consists of 11 folders containing information about the extent of Dr. Stead's community activism, especially with regard to UH's affirmative action and sexual harassment policies. While most of the folders in this series contain policy guidelines, some Equal Rights Amendment folders also hold newsletters, magazine articles, and newspaper clippings.
  - "Affirmative Action Speech," by University President Philip G. Hoffman to Equal Opportunity Council Members, October 21, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - UH Equal Employment Opportunity Policy and Affirmative Action Program (Box 1, Folder 46)
    LD2281.H73995 U533 1974
  - International Women's Year, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Laws Administered by EEOC, OVS KF3464.A6U55 1985
  - EEOC Affirmative Action Guidelines and Employee Selection Procedures, July 1, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Is it Sexual Harassment?" A Workshop Presented by the Office of Affirmative Action, University of Houston, Equal Rights Amendment (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Newsletters, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Articles, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Greater Houston Women's Foundation Excellence Awards: Funded Research Conducted by the University of Houston, Graduate School of Social Work, College of Business Administration, Institute for Diversity and Cross-Cultural Management (Box 1, Folder 54)
    HQ1439.H68G74 1994
  - "Ethics Contest," First Annual Bauer College Leadership and Ethics Week, November 2002 (Box 1, Folder 55)